And now let me make this real for you by showing you some, some diagrams, particularly now looking
이제 도표를 보여드리면서 실감이 나게 해드릴게요 특히 출로라와 훈련하는
at how training works with Chullora, which is how we're actually doing it in practice.
방법에 대해서요 실제로 연습에서 하는 방법이죠
So first of all, let's talk about this forward pass.
먼저 포워드 패스 얘기를 해보죠
So here is a diagram that should be familiar to you because it's the same one I used before.
이 다이어그램은 익숙하실 겁니다 제가 전에 사용한 것과 같거든요
That shows our llama 3.1 base model that we've quantized all the way down to four bits with its 8 billion
라마 3을 보여줬어요 우리가 수량화한 기본 모델은 80억
parameters and the white, all of it is frozen.
매개 변수까지 전부 동결됐어요
We're not going to be changing its weights as part of training, because it would be way too much work,
훈련의 일환으로 무게는 바꾸지 않을 겁니다 할 일도 메모리도
way too much memory, and too slow to try and shift and tweak and optimize these 8 billion parameters.
너무 많고 80억 매개 변수를 변경하고 최적화하는 것도 너무 느리니까요
So what we're seeing here is a bunch of frozen rows of weights, and the ones in yellow are also frozen,
여기 보면 여러 개의 추가 얼어 있는데요 노란색도 얼어 있지만
but they're representing our target modules.
대상 모듈을 나타내요
Which color is going to be applied to.
어떤 색을 적용할지를요
And let's bring in our Lora adapters.
로라 어댑터를 가져오죠
There they are.
저기 있네요
You may remember that to be technically correct, there are in fact two adapters called A and B for
기술적으로 맞는다는 걸 기억하실지 모르겠는데 A와 B라는 어댑터가
each of the different, um target modules they have.
두 개 있어요 각각의 대상 모듈에 대해서요
Dimensionality given by R, and you may remember that alpha is the scaling factor.
R이 부여한 차원성입니다 알파가 배율 요인인 걸 기억하실 거예요
And it just is as simple as the way that these are applied to their target module is that it's alpha
대상 모듈에 적용되는 방식만큼 간단합니다 알파 곱하기 A
times A times B.
곱하기 B죠
Um simple as that.
그게 다예요
So that is our neural network that we know well.
이게 우리가 잘 아는 신경망이에요
And we are going to be training the weights in this, these Laura adapters, which in our case is about
이 로라 어댑터로 웨이트를 훈련할 거예요 이건 약 109MB짜리
109MB worth of, of weights.
웨이트예요
Uh, okay.
네
So then what happens?
그럼 어떻게 되죠?
We have an input prompt over on the left.
왼쪽에 입력 프롬프트가 있어요
It is like price is dollars and then it's the next token.
가격이 달러라면 다음 토큰이 그 다음이죠
We want the model to get good at predicting.
Get in get 예측을 잘해야 해요
The forward pass is when we take that and we in inference mode basically we we put it take it through
전진 패스란 입력 모드를 취하는 건데요 기본적으로 모델로 입력해
the the model to say please predict the next token.
다음 토큰을 예측해달라고 하는 거죠
And so that goes through the model and what comes out the other side is a predicted next token price
모델로 살펴보면 반대쪽에 예상되는 토큰 가격이 나와요
And then 99.
그다음은 99명이에요
And again because we've got we're taking advantage of this simplicity of llama 3.1 that in fact 99 is
다시 말하지만 우린 llama 3의 단순함을 이용하고 있어요 1번, 사실 99는 토큰 하나일
just one token.
뿐이죠
Um, not not.
아닌 건 아니죠
And that will always be the case for any three digit number.
세 자리 숫자라면 언제나 그렇죠
That's not that that's critical, but it does simplify things a bit for us.
그게 중요한 건 아니지만 비트가 우릴 좀 단순화시키죠
So that's the forward pass.
그게 포워드 패스죠
All right.
좋아요
Now onto the loss calculation.
이제 손실 계산을 해 보죠
So here we are again.
다시 모였네요
We've predicted the next token.
다음 토큰을 예측했어요
So now the model is able to look up what or not the model the training process.
이제 모델은 훈련 과정을 살펴볼 수 있어요
The SFT trainer in our case looks up.
우리 같은 경우는 위를 봐요
What was the actual next token.
다음 토큰이 뭐였을까요?
Because we've got the training data, we know the actual next token.
훈련 데이터가 있기 때문에 실제 다음 토큰을 알아요
And what was it?
그게 뭐였죠?
Let's say it was 89.
89라고 치죠
It was lower.
낮았어요
So we were wrong.
우리가 틀렸군요
Wrong by $10.
10달러 차이예요
Um, or wrong.
틀렸을 수도 있고요
By different token, it doesn't know that this represents $10.
다른 토큰으로 이게 10달러라는 걸 몰라요
It just knows it's a different token.
다른 토큰이란 걸 알 뿐이죠
Um, and so there is some kind of a loss.
그래서 상실감이 좀 있어요
And in just a moment I'm going to explain what that loss is and why it's not quite as simple as it just
잠시 후에 손실이 무엇인지 설명하고 다른 토큰으로 사용하면 왜 안 되는지
being a different token.
설명해 드릴게요
There's a technicality there that we'll get to, but for now you can just think of it as it predicted
기술적인 부분을 짚고 넘어가겠지만 일단은 99개까지 예상했다고만 해두죠. Get
99.
it!
The actual value is 89.
실제 가격은 89예요
We have a loss.
손실이 생겼어요
So that's the loss calculation.
그게 손실 계산이고요
Step three is the backward pass that you hear people calling backprop or backward propagation.
세 번째 단계는 뒤로 가기 패스입니다 사람들이 뒤로 가기나 뒤로 전파라고 부르는 걸 들으실 수 있죠
Back propagation.
역증식이죠
Um, and in backprop basically we look back through the network, back we go and we say, all right,
백프롭에서는 네트워크를 통해 살펴봅니다. 그러면 얼마나 비트를
so how much if we if we were to tweak these weights by a little bit, how much would that affect the
약간만 조정하면 얼마나 손실이 발생할까요?
How sensitive is the loss to to those those weights.
저 무게에 대한 상실감이 얼마나 민감하죠?
It gives us what we call the gradients of the weights of the parameters.
매개 변수의 무게의 기울기라는 걸 제공하죠
So when I say weights are synonymous with parameters.
무게는 매개 변수와 동의어예요
Uh, so, uh, how, uh, um, yeah.
그럼 어떻게 네
What are the gradients?
경사도가 어떻게 되죠?
If we were to change those weights, what would it do to the loss?
무게를 바꾸면 손실이 얼마나 커질까요?
Because we want to try and improve things a little bit.
비트 박스를 개선하고 싶거든요
Um, and so those, uh, red triangles are meant to represent Delta, uh, for showing like a gradient
저 빨간 삼각형은 델타를 나타내는 거예요 저기서 일어난 그러데이션 계산을
calculation that's happened there.
보여주기 위해서요
Uh, and then finally we get to the last step, step four optimization.
그리고 마지막 단계로 넘어가죠 4단계 최적화요 Get it
Here it comes.
나오네요
So we've got these gradients.
그래서 이런 경사가 있죠
And what we now need to do is we want to take a tiny step in the right direction.
이제 올바른 방향으로 작은 걸음을 내디뎌야 해요
So we want to update the parameters in our Laura matrices a little tiny bit.
로라 행렬의 매개 변수를 업데이트해야 하는데 비트가 조금 부족해요
So that next time if it gets the same input prompt, the loss will be a bit lower.
다음 번에 같은 inputFrompt를 선택하면 손실이 약간 더 낮아지죠
It would do a bit better.
비트가 더 나을 거예요
So we're taking a step in the right direction, and we use the learning rate to decide how much of a
올바른 방향으로 한 걸음 나아가고 있어요 학습률을 기준으로 얼마나 나아갈지
step to take.
결정하죠
Because as I said before, there are pros and cons of taking smaller or larger steps.
앞서 말했듯이 보폭이 작거나 큰 것에 장단점이 있어요
Um, and you may remember that the optimizer we're using, the Adam W optimizer, does something quite
기억하실지 모르겠지만 애덤 W. 최적화 프로그램은 아주 기발한 방법을 사용했어요
cunning, where it doesn't just use these gradients, it keeps a kind of rolling average of prior gradients,
기존의 그러데이션 수치를 그대로 유지하면서 기존의 그러데이션 수치를 그대로
so that it's being really smart about how to take that step in a way that's most likely to improve things.
유지했죠 그래서 현명하게도 개선할 수 있는 방법을 찾아냈어요
And it's also trying to make sure that we don't do things like overfitting and other dangers that we've
너무 꽉 찬 옷을 입거나 다른 위험을 감수하지 않도록 하는 것이기도
talked about before.
하죠
So we do that.
그렇게 하죠
And what happens is that the Laura adapters are then improved, and as they are applied in the future
로라 어댑터가 개선되고 미래에는 기본 모델에 적용할
to our base model, it will do slightly better.
텐데 조금 더 나아질 거예요
The loss will be a bit lower next time, and that is why you see that the training loss is coming down
다음번에는 손실이 더 적겠죠 그래서 훈련 손실이 줄고 있는 거예요 흔들리는
and our wiggly charts, because it's learning and getting better and better.
도표도요 비트는 배우고 나아지고 있으니까요
And so it's worth noting, of course, that the thing that the weights, the parameters that get changed
여기서 짚고 넘어갈 것은 체중과 변수가 변경된 매개 변수는 로라
are the parameters in the Laura adapters, the green ones, we don't actually change any parameters
어댑터의 녹색 매개 변수입니다 llama 3에서는 어떤 매개
in the llama 3.1 base that is just too big, too many parameters.
변수도 변경하지 않아요 베이스 1이 너무 크고 매개 변수가 너무 많아요
If you were doing ordinary training, fine tuning, not not Laura based, but ordinary, then it would
로라 기반의 훈련이 아닌 평범한 훈련이었다면 라마
be the whole llama 3.1 model that would need to be having gradients calculated and need to be shifted
3 전체가 됐을 거예요 그러데이션을 계산하고 최적화 때 변경해야
during optimization.
하는 모델이죠
And that, of course, is what these big companies like meta.
물론 메타 같은 대기업이 그런 거죠
That's how they've trained llama 3.1in the first place, and they've spent significant amounts of money
라마 3을 그렇게 훈련시켰어요 1인당 그리고 거기에 엄청난 돈을 들였는데
doing it, which which we don't have easy access to, which is why we're using our Lora adapters instead.
우리는 그 돈을 쉽게 구할 수 없어서 로라 어댑터를 대신 쓰고 있는 거예요
So that's the quick summary of optimization in the sorry of the whole of the training process.
지금까지 최적화에 대한 요약이었습니다. 트레이닝 프로세스 전체에서 말이죠.
And I imagine that was probably mostly clear to you already, but I'm hoping that these diagrams of
이미 대부분 명확하게 이해하셨겠지만 이 도표를 보고 이해하셨길
crystallized it for you and mean that everything has fallen into place.
바랍니다 모든 게 제자리를 찾았다는 뜻이죠
And in the next video, I'm just going to explain one more technicality, a very important technicality
다음 강의에서는 기술적인 면을 하나만 더 설명할게요 아주 중요한 기술적 측면으로
about what we mean by the prediction and the loss calculation.
예측과 손실 계산의 의미를 설명해 드리죠
See you then.
그때 봐요